Register of the James Harold Shoemaker Papers, 1924-1983
Hoover Institution Archives
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1947-1969
  - Smith, Elden, 1956 (Folder 86)
  - Snyder, Rixford, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Soga, Shigeo, 1958-1963 (Folder 2)
  - Solomon, Ezra, 1959 (Folder 3)
  - Sorensen, Roger, 1964 (Folder 4)
  - Spalding, Philip E., 1960 (Folder 5)
  - Spector, Alan L., 1963 (Folder 6)
  - Spellacy, E. F., 1963 (Folder 7)
  - Spoehr, Alexander, 1962-1963 (Folder 8)
  - Sprinkel, Beryl W., 1956-1959 (Folder 9)
  - Staebler, Neil, 1962 (Folder 10)
  - Staley, Eugene, 1961 (Folder 11)
  - Stanfield, B. M., 1960-1961 (Folder 12)
  - Steele, Dwight C., 1958 (Folder 13)
  - Stellmacher, H. B., 1963 (Folder 14)
  - Stepp, George A., Jr., 1959 (Folder 15)
  - Stimpson, Harry F., Jr., 1959 (Folder 16)
  - Stokeld, Frederick W., 1966 (Folder 17)
  - Storer, Robert W., 1956 (Folder 18)
  - Straus, Oscar S., 1961-1965 (Folder 19)
  - Straus, Ralph I., 1961 (Folder 20)
  - Surveys and Research Corporation (Boyd Ladd, Ralph J. Watkins), 1964-1966 (Folder 21)
  - Sutro and Company (Felix Juda, Jay Maguire), 1966 (Folder 22)
  - Suzuki, Tatsuro, 1962 (Folder 23)
  - Swenson, Mr. and Mrs. David, 1960 (Folder 24)
  - Taft, Philip, 1963-1966 (Folder 25)
  - Tai Ping Carpeting Salon, 1963 (Folder 26)
  - Takamine, Yoshito, 1963 (Folder 27)
  - Takayama, Tadao, 1963 (Folder 28)
  - Tanner, Harold B., 1960 (Folder 29)
  - Tatsuno, Howard, 1958 (Folder 30)
  - Taylor, Amos E., 1959 (Folder 31)
  - Taylor, Elizabeth H., 1960 (Folder 32)
  - Taylor, Frank J., 1959 (Folder 33)
  - Taylor, George, 1963 (Folder 34)
  - Taylor, William H., 1960 (Folder 35)
  - Tead, Ordway, 1965. Includes correspondence with E. John Wallace (Folder 36)
  - Tebbutt, Mr. and Mrs. Arthur R., 1965 (Folder 37)
  - Terborgh, George, 1969 (Folder 38)
  - Thayer, Robert, 1959. Includes correspondence with Laurence H. Snyder (Folder 39)
  - Tinker, Spencer, 1963 (Folder 40)
  - Todorovich, M., 1965 (Folder 41)
  - Toland, Robert P., 1964 (Folder 42)
  - Tolles, N. Arnold, 1966 (Folder 43)
  - Tomita, Mr. and Mrs. Tadao, 1960-1962 (Folder 44)
  - Turner, Lowell F., 1962 (Folder 45)
  - University of Hawaii (John Allison, W. Todd Furniss, Thomas H. Hamilton, Morton M. Rosenberg, Laurence H. Snyder, Willard Wilson), 1959-1965 (Folder 46)
  - University of Hong Kong (E. Stuart Kirby), 1961-1965 (Folder 47)
  - Ureke, George, 1963 (Folder 48)
  - Van derVeur, Paul W., 1961 (Folder 49)
  - Vetch, H., 1961 (Folder 50)
  - Vogt, Herbert J., 1959 (Folder 51)
  - Voll, Rudolph, 1965 (Folder 52)
  - Walker, Kenneth F., 1962 (Folder 53)
  - Walsh, Floyd E., 1961 (Folder 54)
  - Warner, H. H., 1960 (Folder 55)
  - Watkins, Ralph, 1959-1962 (Folder 56)
  - Watumull, Mrs. G. J., 1963 (Folder 57)
  - Weigel, Marshall J., 1960. Includes a letter to Max L. Pilliard about James Shoemaker (Folder 58)
  - Wermel, Michael T., 1960 (Folder 59)
  - Wernette, J. Philip, 1969 (Folder 60)
  - Western Interstate Commission for Higher Education (Robert H. Kroepsch, Terry F. Lunsford), 1961-1966 (Folder 61)
  - Western Meat Packers Association, Inc. (Norman H. Maffit, Richard Penhallow), 1959 (Folder 62)
  - Weston, J. Fred, 1962 (Folder 63)
  - Wheeler, Oliver P., 1960 (Folder 64)
  - Whiteside, Henry O., 1963 (Folder 65)
  - Wilburn, Berney T., 1962 (Folder 66)
  - Wilcox, F. R., 1963 (Folder 67)
  - Williamson, Harold F., 1963 (Folder 68)
  - Withington, Leonard, 1958-1963. Includes a letter to Charles B. Buscher (Folder 69)
  - Witmer, John L., 1963 (Folder 70)
  - Wittenberger, Park, 1964-1965 (Folder 71)
  - Wong, Walter W. T., 1963 (Folder 72)
  - Woodcock, Robert L., 1961 (Folder 73)
  - Wooding, Richard P., 1962 (Folder 74)
  - Yamagiwa, Joseph K., 1962 (Folder 75)
  - Yamaguchi, Ralph T., 1963 (Folder 76)
  - Yamashita, Seiichi, 1962 (Folder 77)
  - Yamato, Kei, 1963-1966. Also includes correspondence with Hiram L. Fong, Daniel K. Inouye, Spark M. Matsunga (Folder 78)
  - Yamauchi, Carole, 1965 (Folder 79)
  - Young Women's Christian Association of OAHU (Katherine Lind, Joan Nielsen), 1963 (Folder 80)
  - Zellerbach, J. D., 1963 (Folder 81)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1924-1968
  - "American Assistance to Europe," n.d. Revised typewritten outline (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "Basic Postwar Trends and the Developing Strength of Communism as Determinants of American Foreign Policy," n.d. Prepared for the Social Science Association, Honolulu, Hawaii. Typescript (Folder 2)
  - "Broad Goals for Economic Development in Hawaii," n.d. Statement prepared at the request of the President of the Chamber of Commerce, Honolulu, Hawaii. Typescript. Includes a letter to M. L. Randolph (Folder 3)
  - "Economic Transformations Since the War," n.d. Typescript (Folder 4)
  - "Employment in Hawaii in 1961," n.d. Typescript (Folder 5)
  - Labor Trends in Hawaii, n.d. Printed copy (Folder 6)
  - "Present Position of and Outlook for Hawaii," n.d. (author uncertain). Typescript (Folder 7)
  - "Prospective Changes in Hawaii During the Decade Ahead: Their Implications for Educational Policy," n.d. Typescript (Folder 8)
  - Statement on the development of the Hawaiian economy to be presented at the Maritime Administration - Maritime Subsidy Board, American President Lines, Ltd., n.d. Typescript (Folder 9)
  - "The Controlled Economy," n.d. Typescript manuscripts
    - Unidentified fragments (Folder 10)
    - Titled sections (Folder 11)
      - 'Japan'
      - 'Specific Forms of Economic Control'
      - 'The Objectives of Economic Planning'
      - 'Long-time Goals as a Guide to Current Policies'
      - 'Pressure Groups'
      - 'The Controlled Economy in Action'
      - 'The Trend Toward the Controlled Economy'
    - Chapter I (Folder 12)
    - Chapter II (Folder 13)
    - Chapter III (Folder 14)
  - "The Economy of Hawaii 1960-1970," n.d. Typescript (Folder 15)
  - "The Outlook for Tourism in New Zealand: Developing Changes that Will Affect Travel in the South Pacific," n.d. Address, Travel Conference, Auckland, New Zealand. Typescript. Includes correspondence with George Chaplin (Folder 16)
  - "An Introduction to the Study of Japan's Colonial Policies," 1924. A thesis for the degree of Master of Arts, Graduate College, State University of Iowa, Iowa. Typescript (Folder 17)
  - Labor in the Territory of Hawaii, 1939 June. Printed copy (Folder 18)
  - Labor Conditions in Hawaii, 1941. Printed copy (Folder 19)
  - "Notes on Korea's Postwar Economic Position," 1947 September. A study to be presented at the Tenth Conference of the Institute of Pacific Relations, Stratford-upon-Avon, England. Typescript (Folder 20)
  - "Basic Economic Trends and their Relation to Hawaii," 1947 December 3. Address, the Sixty-Seventh Annual Meeting of the Hawaiian Sugar Planters' Association, Hawaii. Printed copy (Folder 21)
  - The Economy of Hawaii in 1947, 1948. Printed copy (Folder 22)
  - Untitled, 1948 February 27. Typescript (Folder 23)
  - "Economic and Labor Conditions in Hawaii," Monthly Labor Reviews, Bureau of Labor Statistics, United States Department of Labor, 1948 May-June. Printed copy (Folder 24)
  - "Labor Trends in Hawaii," Monthly Labor Review, Bureau of Labor Statistics, United States Department of Labor, 1948 June. Printed copy (Folder 25)
  - "Hawaii Today," Eastern World, 1949 December. Printed copy (Folder 26)
  - "The Economy of Hawaii in 1951," Paradise of the Pacific, 1951 June. Printed copy (Folder 27)
  - "Hawaiian Manufactures Show Marked Growth: Official Report Reveals Increasing Importance of Industrial Production in the Islands," Advertiser, 1958 January 19. Typescript (Folder 28)
  - "Technical Advances as a Factor in the Economic Development of Hawaii," 1958 January 22. Outline prepared for the Molokai Education Association Conference, Hawaii? Typescript (Folder 29)
  - "Vegetable Production in Hawaii," 1958 June 3. Report on the Conference conducted by the Trade Committee, Chamber of Commerce, Honolulu, Hawaii. Typescript (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - "Vegetable Production in the Hawaiian Economy - Its History and Outlook," 1958 June 3. Outline prepared for the Vegetable Conference, Hawaii? Typescript (Folder 2)
  - "Agriculture in the Economy of Hawaii," 1958 June 21. Brief summary of a talk for the Young Farmers Convention, Hilo, Hawaii? Typescript (Folder 3)
  - "Hawaii and the Business of Defense," 1958 August 11. Talk, Princess Kaiulani Meeting House, Hawaii. Typescript (Folder 4)
  - "Research for the Benefit of Small Business," 1958 September 10-12. Speech, Production and Marketing Conference, Hawaii. Typescript (Folder 5)
  - "Hawaii Experiencing a Period of Record Expansion," 1958 September 15. Typescript (Folder 6)
  - Untitled, 1958 November 17. Small Business Conference, Hilo, Hawaii? Typewritten outline for a speech? (Folder 7)
  - "Tourism," 1958 December 11. Paper, Western Region Republican Conference, Princess Kaiulani Meeting House, Hawaii. Typescript (Folder 8)
  - "What are the Economic Prospects for the Next Two Years?" 1959 January? Typewritten outline for a speech, Small Business Management Institute, Hawaii. (Folder 9)
  - "Business in Hawaii: The Short and Long Range Outlook," Honolulu Advertiser, 1959 January 1. Typescript (Folder 10)
  - "Hawaii's Expanding Economy: Some Basic Growth Factors," Honolulu Star-Bulletin, 1959 January 1. Typescript (Folder 11)
  - "The Business Outlook in Hawaii," article for Hawaii Times. 1959 January 1. Typescript (Folder 12)
  - "Economic Development: Tourism as a Factor in the Growth of the Economy of Hawaii," 1959 January 16. Paper, Pre-Legislative Conference, Hawaii, Typescript (Folder 13)
  - "Two Factors Affecting the Growth of Tourism," 1959 January 21. Speech, Conference on Tourism, Tolani Palace, Hawaii? Holograph notes and typescript (Folder 14)
  - "The Economy of Hawaii Today: A Brief Summary," 1959 February 6. Typescript (Folder 15)
  - Statement, Hearings at the Committee on Economic Development, House of Representatives, Hawaii, 1959 February 9. Typescript (Folder 16)
  - "Hawaii in 1980," Honolulu Advertiser, 1959 March 5. Typescript. Includes a memorandum (Folder 17)
  - Statement on credit, requested by Senator Nelson K. Doi, Chairman, Senate Committee on Economic Development, Hawaii, for the hearing on 1959 March 17. This statement was also used for the hearing on 1959 April 7, House Committee on Economic Development, Hawaii, (Howard Miyake, Chairman). Typescript (Folder 18)
  - "The Relative Position of the 'Big Five' in the Economy of Hawaii," 1959 April 28. Typescript (Folder 19)
  - Address, Kapiolani Technical School Graduation, Hawaii? 1959 May 31. Typescript (Folder 20)
  - "Business in the State of Hawaii: Past Growth and Present Outlook," 1959 June 15. Typescript. Includes a short resumi of James Shoemaker (Folder 21)
  - "The Economy of Hawaii," Encyclopedia Brittanica, 1959 July 1. Typescript (Folder 22)
  - Outline for a speech on mainland business and trade tour, 1959 September 8. Typescript (Folder 23)
  - "Hawaii - Growth and Potentials of Our Island State," Burroughs Clearing House, 1959 November 16. Typescript (Folder 24)
  - "Our Western Frontier," 1959 November 18. Speech, Society of American Foresters, Sheraton Palace Hotel, San Francisco, California. Holograph notes, typescript and photocopy (Folder 25)
  - "Business and Banking in Hawaii: The 1960 Outlook," 1959 December 21. Typescript (Folder 26)
  - "The Business Outlook in Hawaii," 1959 December 22. Typescript (Folder 27)
  - "The Economy of Hawaii 1960-1970," Advertiser, 1959 December 29. Typescript (Folder 28)
  - "Proposed Tax Reductions," 1960 March 22. Typescript (Folder 29)
  - "Hawaii a Year Later - The Effects of Statehood," United States Investor, 1960 April 26. Typescript (Folder 30)
  - "Korean Leadership in Hawaii," 1960 April 27. Typescript (Folder 31)
  - "What Your Employer and Your Company Expect of You as a Graduate Entering Business Life," 1960 April 27. Typescript (Folder 32)
  - "Prospective Opportunities for Graduates," 1960 April 29. Typescript outline for a talk, Punahou, Hawaii? (Folder 33)
  - "Mainland and Foreign Investment in Hawaii," 1960 May. Typescript (Folder 34)
  - "Investment as a Growth Factor in Hawaii," 1960 July 22. Typescript (Folder 35)
  - "Training and Employmnt Placement," 1960 November 16-19. Typescript abstract for a speech, White House Conference on Children and Youth, Hawaii (Folder 36)
  - "The 1961 Outlook for Business in Hawaii," 1960 December 23. Typescript (Folder 37)
  - "The Outlook for Neighbor Island Hotels with Special Reference to Inter - Island Resorts Hotels," 1960 December 23. Typescript (Folder 38)
  - "The 1961 Outlook," Honolulu Advertiser, 1961 January 9. Typescript. Includes a letter to Joanne Braunberns (Folder 39)
  - "Hawaii - The Growing Islands of Our Newest State," Commercial and Financial Chronicle, 1961 February 23. Typescript (Folder 40)
  - "Notes on Europe," 1961 May 10. Typescript. Includes a press release (Folder 41)
  - "The 1962 Outlook in Hawaii," Bank of Hawaii Review of Business and Economic Conditions, 1961 December 20. Typescript (Folder 42)
  - "Hawaii Economy Outstanding as Long-Term Potential," Investment Dealers' Digest, 1962 April 2. Printed copy (Folder 43)
  - "Hurricane Winds of Economic Change," 1962 April 2. Paper, Social Science Association meeting, Honolulu, Hawaii. Typescript (Folder 44)
  - "Hawaii as a Factor in Pacific Trade," 1962 October 21-23. Paper, Inland Empire Waterways Association, Twenty-Ninth Annual Convention, Seattle, Washington. Typescript (Folder 45)
  - "Five Years of Growth: Economic Advances in Hawaii since 1957," 1962 October 29. Typescript (Folder 46)
  - "Effect of HR 8000 on Economic Relations with Japan," 1963 August 23. Statement, Committee on Ways and Means, House of Representatives, Hawaii. Typescript (Folder 47)
  - "The Economy of Hawaii Today: Its Relation to the Economy of Japan," 1963 November 13. Talk, Honolulu Japanese Chamber of Commerce, Hawaii. Typescript outline (Folder 48)
  - "Hawaii's Past Growth Forces Continue in Strength," The Commercial and Financial Chronicle, 1963 November 28. Printed copy (Folder 49)
  - "Alaska and Hawaii: Potentials for Interstate Business," 1968 January 16. Typescript (Folder 50)
- UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT OFFICE FILE, 1941-1961
  - Board of Economic Warfare, report, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Military Government Division
    - General (Folder 2)
    - Civil Affairs
      - Handbooks
        - Austria (Folder 3)
        - Greece (Folder 4)
        - Hungary (Folder 5)
        - Italy (Folder 6)
        - Japan (Folder 7)
        - Norway (Folder 8)
        - Romania (Folder 9)
      - Information guide (Folder 10)
    - Language guides (Folder 11)
    - Memoranda (Folder 12)
    - Military dictionary (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Radio broadcasts (Folder 2)
    - Reports
      - Undated (Folder 3)
      - 1945 (Folder 4)
  - Office of Strategic Bombing Survey
    - General (Folder 5-6)
    - Air defense plans (Folder 7)
    - Charts (Folder 8-9)
    - Correspondence, 1945-1946 (Folder 10)
    - Maps (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    - Memoranda, 1945 (Folder 3)
    - Notes, n.d. (Folder 4)
    - Reports
      - Undated (Folder 5)
      - 1944 (Folder 6)
  - United States Navy Mission
    - General (Folder 7)
    - Memoranda, 1946 (Folder 8)
  - United States Army Military Government in Korea, 1946
    - Chart (Folder 9)
    - Correspondence (Folder 10)
    - Memoranda (Folder 11)
    - Printed matter (Folder 12)
    - Reports (Folder 13-14)
  - National Security Resources Board, n.d.
    - Printed matter (Folder 15)
    - Reports (Folder 16)
  - United States Civil Service Commission
    - Correspondence, 1954-1961 (Folder 17)
    - Memoranda, 1954 (Folder 18)
- BANK OF HAWAII OFFICE FILE, 1946-1969
  - General (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Folder 20)
  - Economy
    - Correspondence, 1950 (Folder 21)
    - Memoranda
      - 1958-1959 (Folder 22)
      - 1965 (Folder 23)
    - Minutes of meetings
      - Undated (Folder 24)
      - 1958-1961 (Folder 25)
    - Newsletters, 1959-1967 (Folder 26)
    - Notes, n.d. Holograph (Folder 27)
    - Reports
      - Undated (Folder 28)
      - 1950-1955 (Folder 29)
      - 1956-1958 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - 1959-1960 (Folder 2)
      - 1961-1962 (Folder 3)
      - 1964 (Folder 4)
      - 1966-1969 (Folder 5)
    - Statements, 1961 (Folder 6)
  - Education
    - Minutes of meetings, 1964 (Folder 7)
    - Printed matter, 1967 (Folder 8)
    - Reports
      - 1953 (Folder 9)
      - 1956 (Folder 10)
      - 1959-1960 (Folder 11)
      - 1964 (Folder 12)
  - Housing
    - Correspondence, 1946-1963 (Folder 13)
    - Reports
      - Undated (Folder 14)
      - 1966 (Folder 15)
    - Statements, 1959-1961 (Folder 16)
  - Japan - United States Amity and Trade Centennial Committee
    - General (Folder 17)
    - Correspondence
      - 1960
        - April-May (Folder 18-19)
        - July-October (Folder 20-23)
        - December (Folder 24)
      - 1961
        - January-February (Folder 25-26)
        - April (Folder 27)
        - November-December (Folder 28-29)
      - 1962, January (Folder 30)
    - Clippings (Folder 31)
    - Newsletters (Folder 32)
    - Press releases (Folder 33)
    - Statements
      - Undated (Folder 34)
      - 1960 (Folder 35)
  - Printed matter (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Public relations, minutes of meetings, 1959 (Folder 2)
  - Tourism
    - Memoranda, 1959-1960 (Folder 3)
    - Notes, n.d. Holograph (Folder 4)
    - Reports
      - 1953 (Folder 5)
      - 1956 (Folder 6)
      - 1957 (Folder 7)
      - 1961 (Folder 8)
      - 1962 (Folder 9)
      - 1955-1965 (Folder 10)
    - Statements, n.d. (Folder 11)
  - Welfare
    - General (Folder 12)
    - Reports, n.d. (Folder 13)
    - Statements, 1960 (Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 15)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1942-1970
  Brochures, correspondence, memoranda, newsletters, press releases, printed matter, programs, reports and statements
  - Alaska (Box 13, Folder 16-17)
  - Communism (Folder 18)
  - Economy (Folder 19-20)
  - Education (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
  - Germany. Strenger, A. D., "Insight into the Nazi Industrial War Machine with Ideas and Suggestions Relating to Occupation, Chances of Germany's Inside Collapse, Prevention of Germany's Rearmament and the Post War Period," 1943. Speech. Typescript (Folder 3)
  - Guyana (Folder 4)
  - Hawaii
    - Hall, Jack, radio broadcast, 1952 June 6. Typescript (Folder 5)
    - Stevens, E. Leigh, "Community - Wide Cooperation Fights Unemployment in Hawaii," n.d. Typescript (Folder 6)
  - Netherlands (Folder 7)
  - New Zealand (Folder 8-10)
  - Peru (Folder 11)
  - Surinam (Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 13)
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL, 1924-1942
  - Certificate for the degree of Master of Arts from the University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa, 1924 (Box 15)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1954-1958
  - 2 prints depicting James Shoemaker with others; 2 prints of James Shoemaker addressing an audience? and 1 print of an exhibit? (Envelope Env. A)